<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hanj Does Coding]]></title>
  <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-04T10:33:38-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hannah Jane]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/04/week-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-04T09:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/04/week-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>ActiveRecord, Sinatra, RegEx, and Cronuts</h3>

<p>As I look at the things we reviewed this week, it seems like we&rsquo;ve covered a lot in a little bit of time. Each week we hit the ground running, and by the time we make it to Friday I am always left some disorientation as I realize another week is over. Our Friday morning blogging ritual allows me the time to review, process, and remember the week past, something I think is critical to the learning process. As a side note, our blogging process made me think of a quote from C.S. Lewis, one of my favorite writers and theologians, &ldquo;Whenever you are fed up with life, start writing: ink is a great cure of all human ills.&rdquo; I may not be taking ink to paper right now (although I do that as well), but this is close enough and way more tech besides.</p>

<p>All of that being said, I really enjoyed our workshops on ActiveRecord and database structuring. Not only did we learn a lot about how this will affect us in our own ventures in applications, it also increasingly shed light on the structure of websites and user interfaces that I already use. I enjoy looking at websites and thinking through their potential database structure.</p>

<p>We then moved onto our SimStackworld Project&mdash;our first web application. This project started to bring together a lot of the concepts that we had been learning over the past several weeks. It involved Ruby, databases, and understanding how the internet works. As a side note I&rsquo;d like to thank my brothers for exposing me to the world of gaming&mdash;there are many conversations here that I can follow because of the minimal amount of of knowledge I gained through living with you through the World of War Craft and Call of Duty years. Cheers to y&#8217;all. I enjoyed this project, but we definitely still had a lot of help from David and Nimit. At one point David commented that I was in &ldquo;git hell.&rdquo; Yes, that feels about accurate. The building blocks are starting to come together, and I think after doing this project I have a better idea of how I could deploy a simple web application on my own. Hopefully this weekend will allow some more time to review the intricacies of the project that I may have stepped over while executing it. I hope to play around with that a little more this weekend, and I&rsquo;m sure as we start on the web crawler project this will bring forth even more questions and capabilities.</p>

<p>This week I&rsquo;ve been trying to brainstorm more about the kind of projects that I want to work on. Not only for my large end of the semester project, but even just little weekend and night projects to help me practice what I&rsquo;m learning. In this learning environment, and in code especially, I think my best chance at developing (no pun intended) sharp coding skills is to build as many things as I can. I&rsquo;m not saying I want to be a machine that cranks out unsophisticated applications, but I think the act of attempting to write some code on my own will increase my confidence in my own ability to learn and execute, and also give me a better idea of the kind of programming job that I want to pursue after graduation.</p>

<p>As a side note, New York is growing on me in some ways, and in some ways I think I may grow crazy here. I love the accessibility&mdash; you can get anything you want here (cronuts, ramen burger&mdash;that&rsquo;s on the food agenda for this weekend). But sometimes I miss the green mountains, and I want to feel grass between my toes without having to go 50 blocks up to central park. And then there are the strange and confused looks when I tell someone my name. Oh, and I miss my dogs. Also, what&rsquo;s it with everyone here and &ldquo;juicing&rdquo;? Everywhere I turn everyone is talking about how they want to do a &ldquo;juice fast.&rdquo; Mmmm, not me, I&rsquo;ll take my bagels and my cronuts and my tacos. On a more positive note, I love how much you walk here&mdash; even though I sit for the majority of the day I have yet to experience back issues, and I feel overall healthy. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see if I end up here post Fullstack; in many ways I&rsquo;d be sad to start my coding career apart from my fellow Fullstackers. I can already see where New York would be a great community to launch a career in tech, and that draw may be enough to make me want to plant my feet here a little bit more permanently.</p>

<p>The cronut hunt is still on. I discovered that the bakery is about a block off my walk on my way to school, so I&rsquo;ve started taking a detour everyday to checkout the line. Hopefully when the weather cools off a little bit people&rsquo;s cronut cravings will ebb (not mine though). I&rsquo;m also planning on making a reservation for some cronuts. It will happen people, bear with me.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to start setting some goals. I&rsquo;ve always enjoyed this process and I think it keeps me focused. Normally, I was in situations where goal setting was a natural part of the start of the semester, but with all the craziness of moving up here I&rsquo;ve neglected this ritual. So I&rsquo;m going to start small. Goals for this weekend: recover and rest&mdash;I think I may be coming down with something; attempt the Sinatra Linker project on Saturday (hence, come into Fullstack this Saturday); brush up on my hash syntax and regular expressions work, a little review never hurt anyone; find a ramen burger (I don&rsquo;t know why I&rsquo;ve latched onto this idea, but I&rsquo;m going for it. I may have some foodie tendencies); and lastly, but certainly not the least important, cheer on my DAWGS as they show Tennessee how to play some real football (this may be happening at Fullstack as the game is at 3:30&mdash;but hey, what are our double monitors for if not some live football streaming?). Oh, and I want to fix my octomailer configuration so that it sends out a link to my blog, and not just the content. Have a good one, friends.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two Weeks and Counting]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/27/two-weeks-and-counting/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-27T09:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/27/two-weeks-and-counting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Blackjack, Ruby, Databases, and Cronuts</h3>

<p>This week has flown by. Each day is so full and before I know it, it&rsquo;s the end of the week. It makes me realize how fast these 12 weeks are going to go and how I need to be taking advantage of every minute of them.</p>

<p>This week started off with the blackjack project. This project involved two main tasks&mdash;writing the code that would generate a blackjack game between a dealer and a player, and writing the tests that would ensure that the code was going to work the way you anticipated. Using test driven development in real life is as hard as it sounds. Not only do you have to try and write code that executes what you want, but you have to write a test that passes based on whether you write that code correctly. In reality, it takes a ton of time on the front end, but when you are done you know you have code that is functioning how it should (assuming you wrote good tests&hellip; but you know what happens when you assume). This exercise was really difficult at first, but as time went on it became more natural and your brain learns to switch between the two different objectives. I think I&rsquo;ll probably try and work through this project again this weekend, or at least review it again. It was really helpful in conceptualizing what was going on in your code and how to write effective tests.</p>

<p>We then switched gears to databases. I think some people found this topic lackluster and a necessary evil, but I found it really interesting! I love the idea of being able to extract very exact information. It gives you access to so many different things, and is so applicable in the real world. When learning SQL it was more a matter of getting syntax and little tricks down. I&rsquo;m by no means an expert, but I think it&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ll play around with more, especially as we start building web apps and potentially gathering data on users. I think as a student of international affairs and public administration I&rsquo;ve always been shown the power of data, and I&rsquo;m excited to have a better understanding of how to access and use it.</p>

<p>From SQL we transitioned over to a project of building our own Active Record(a rails feature), called Simple Record. Once I grasped what we were doing in this project I thought it was really cool! We basically built a way to access a databse(in our case SQL) using the Ruby language. There was a lot going on in this project, and once we were into it we had hundreds of lines of code. And of course, David showed us how we could condense that all down, deeming much of our code unnecessary. But hey! I struggled through it and I think it was worth it for the cognitive gains. I definitely gained a better understanding of what is going on in Active Record, and this weekend I plan on taking another look at what we built for the Simple Record project and making sure I&rsquo;m understanding what&rsquo;s going on at each step.</p>

<p>I think this week has been a transitional week. Now that I am getting my bearings, I&rsquo;m starting to see the dots connect, gaining more understanding, and getting excited about what&rsquo;s to come. But I&rsquo;m probably still struggling to gain confidence in myself as a programmer. I second guess my self alot, defer to my partner&rsquo;s opinion, and occasionally make some self deprecating jokes (a very unbecoming habit that I&rsquo;m trying to stop). I think this weekend I need to just get my head straight. As David mentinoed in our one-on-one last week &ldquo;The computer won&rsquo;t judge you.&rdquo; I don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;s so much of a lack of confidence as much as it is self consicousness. I can feel it starting to drop away as more concepts click. All in all, I feel like I&rsquo;m on the upswing. The basic concept coding hill doesn&rsquo;t seem quite as steep as it use to, and I&rsquo;m starting to enjoy our projects more. This weekend and the beginning of next week will really be about grounding everything I&rsquo;ve learned so far, and gearing up to take on even more difficult coding challenges. I can&rsquo;t wait to see what the next week holds!</p>

<p>P.S. I tried for cronuts today. No luck, the line was around the block. Next week I&rsquo;m going to try again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[End of First Week]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/20/end-of-first-week/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T09:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/20/end-of-first-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>The First Week Comes to a Close</h1>

<p>The first week at Fullstack has definitely been a challenging one. As I&rsquo;ve told a couple of friends lately, &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve never been so intellecutally humbled and challenged.&rdquo; One of the biggest take aways has just been learning how to switch the way I approcah problems and understanding. While I completed nearly all of the preterm coursework, there is nothing like getting your hands dirty and actually trying to build something. This week has really taught me how to take each problem and break it down into logical steps, and in that I&rsquo;ve realized that sometimes the hardest part is just figuring out where to start.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed buidling the profile page on the first day. It was an unintimdating way to get started, and start learning how to play around with things. The hardest thing for me this week was probably the octomailer project. I think I really struggled with just figuring out what the next step was, and it just wasn&rsquo;t clicking. I understand how we were using symbols and hashes and arrays on the more theoretical level, but when it came to actually writing the code and moving through it step by step I really struggled.I reviewed the project with my finished code afterwards and that helped solidfy the thought process a little bit. Since I hadn&rsquo;t gotten to haiku yet, I started on that, and I&rsquo;ve really enjoyed working on building that so far! I really like how I can see the logical next steps&mdash; that project is clicking more for me than the octomailer.
I think moving forward my biggest challenge is just overcoming the doubt that creeps in when something doesn&rsquo;t click immediately. I know I&rsquo;m capable of learning how to do this, but I often find myself doubting my ability to learn and execute.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Week]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/first-week/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T12:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/first-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First Days at Fullstack
The first days have already been full of learning and sometimes, new frustrations. I don&rsquo;t know if I ever realized how many things can go wrong with your computer&mdash;this morning we spent the better half of the day trying to reinstall ruby in order for me to write this blog post. Luckily, David and Nimit are master coders and I think we worked it all. I&rsquo;m going to download some updated software and hopefully that will help avoid some problems in the future. This afternoon we start on Ruby, so get ready for an update on that!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
