<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Hanj Does Coding]]></title>
  <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-18T11:39:41-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Hannah Jane]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Picking up Steam]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/17/picking-up-steam/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-17T17:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/17/picking-up-steam</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Rails on Rails</h2>

<p>This week we started to build our first big Rails project. To be honest, I was completely nervous and freaked out about starting a group project on Rails. I felt like we had barely been exposed to the framework by working in it on StackWorld. But as is usually the case, I think David and Nimit were right to throw us into a big group project this soon. I think I have a natural tendency to want to sort it all out before I actually do anything, and sometimes the most effective way to learn is to just do it&mdash;break some things (a lot of things), and then learn how to fix them.</p>

<p>My group was one of the groups with four members. In some ways, I think this gave us an advantage. Four minds working on a problem, three other people to ask questions when something goes wrong. But it also meant we had to be a little more organized and had to make sure that we were keeping track of everyone&rsquo;s work. Our group was really into the SCRUM model and using Trello. Actually, we loved <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a>. We loved scrumming. We held scrum meetings two or three times a day (depending on the issues that arise and the work flow). I honestly don&rsquo;t know how other groups kept track of their project without it. Y&#8217;all are crazy. Trello really allowed us to see our progress and also helped us define our goals around our project more clearly. There wasn&rsquo;t wasted effort because we knew the tasks that had to be completed. I think I&rsquo;ll continue to use Trello for future group projects and even for projects that I&rsquo;m working on independently. I love the over view that it gives you, and the ability to see the longer term goals as well as the details. Kudos and thanks to the people of Trello.</p>

<p>Back to Rails. What&rsquo;s neat about Rails is basically everything. There are a ton of built in conventions and helper methods defined for you. It anticipates what you will want and need and it practically hands you a good bit of this on a platter. But things aren&rsquo;t all ruby and roses in Rails. Rails conventions are great. Until you break them. Accidentally. Or you name something with or without the desired &rsquo;s&#8217;. Note to all: grammar IS important. Typos will cause death by error messages. Don&rsquo;t be fooled, that comma matters. You may spend an hour deciphering an error message and trying all different types of syntax for a route and come to find out that you were missing a comma. Not that that&rsquo;s ever happened to me&hellip; But really, as you dig in more to the set up it all starts to make more sense. I&rsquo;m definitely not all there yet, but it&rsquo;s getting more natural. I trust my intuition more, and I&rsquo;m not as scared to break something. If I do, that&rsquo;s okay. I just won&rsquo;t push it up. Or I&rsquo;ll do a stash. Or I&rsquo;ll git reset &mdash;hard. I may have over utilized that tool in the beginning of our project haha. Git is a whole other story. But it is magic as well and I love it.</p>

<p>On a more personal level, this week has definitely been a tipping point. I think learning any new skill is a challenge and can bring about frustrations and doubts. And I think I let that get in my head for awhile. And the crazy thing was that I knew it was happening. I knew that I was letting self doubt and a lack of confidence affect my work and learning curve. I think this week I may have overcome that, or at least started that process. Coding became WAY more fun as I started to trust my instincts more, and started to solve some problems on my own. It became more like a puzzle and I was the one with the pieces, and I just had to figure out how to put them together. Previously, it was more like I had the puzzle and I couldn&rsquo;t figure out a way to open to box. Haha Or something along those lines. About halfway through our project Dave was over helping &ldquo;The Dream Team&rdquo; with a problem. Shout out to the other half of the dream team, <a href="www.wensontsai.github.io">Wenson</a>. If you want to be inspired and laugh and gain some wisdom click that link. Anyway, Dave noted that &ldquo;I always have the right intuition but I hesitate.&rdquo; I may have paraphrased that slightly, but the message is the same. So this weekend I&rsquo;m going to try to build a mini app, let myself make some mistakes, and trust myself to figure them out. Or give it the good ol college try. I&rsquo;m really excited about continuing along this journey and becoming an even better developer.</p>

<p>Goals
1. Build a mini app on Rails this weekend
2. Blog at least once a week besides Fridays
3. Go on a walk or run during lunch or after class at least twice a week now that we have lockers at Fullstack (upgrades, y&#8217;all. upgrades)</p>

<p>In the spirit of our J.R.R. Tolkien Quote Fridays&hellip;</p>

<p>“It&rsquo;s the job that&rsquo;s never started as takes longest to finish.” <em>The Lord of the Rings</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git it, Girl]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/12/git-it/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T11:51:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/12/git-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I mentioned in my previous post, I&rsquo;ve been thinking a lot about &ldquo;women in tech&rdquo;. I think I can account for this for several reasons. The first being the obvious imbalance in the numbers. Imon and I hold down the female fort in our cohort, now with back up from Charlotte. We are constantly outnumebred and are also two of the younger members of the class. All that&rsquo;s fine, but it&rsquo;s definitely makes for a different culture (think GTA and WofWC over Jcrew and The Kardashians). . And then there are those outside of the classroom. Whenever I tell someone what I&rsquo;m doing in New York, they never seem to believe me on the first go round. I get some variation of &ldquo;Coding? Like for computers?&rdquo; Yes, &ldquo;coding for computers.&rdquo; I always wonder what &ldquo;other coding&rdquo; activity they are thinking of when I get this question. This is typically followed up by a &ldquo;what was your major&rdquo; and further shock when they learn that is unrelated to anything STEM. However, my male counterparts have yet to mention any similar encounters. Maybe they are just being mum on the matter. Or maybe no one is surprised that they want to learn how to code.</p>

<p>In a way, I don&rsquo;t mind being a novelty, and I don&rsquo;t mind shattering people&rsquo;s expectations. I&rsquo;m certainly not the first female that has decided to be a developer and I sure won&rsquo;t be the last. To me, what&rsquo;s important is the work I produce. I don&rsquo;t want to be a &ldquo;girl in tech&rdquo;; I want to be a great developer who happens to lack a Y chromosome. What&rsquo;s interesting is seeing this paradigm change as I make this life change. I&rsquo;m excited to see more awesome leaders and developers in the field who happen to be women.</p>

<p>And yet, while there is change in the air, the glaring imbalance is still there. Recently Twitter filed for IPO with an all male board, all male investors, and all male executive officers (except for one, who has been on the job for 5 weeks and is general counsel, so she hardly counts as ). To read more about it, check out this article by the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/05/technology/as-tech-start-ups-surge-ahead-women-seem-to-be-left-behind.html?_r=0">New York Times</a>.  Did I mention that half of Twitter&rsquo;s users are women? Sometimes it&rsquo;s moments like these when you grasp the reality of the imbalance. In a way, it puts more pressure on you to perform&mdash;to not fit the stereotype and to build things that kick ass. Everyone wants that, but I think there&rsquo;s an extra pressure (pressure from themselves) there for women to be exceed expectations.</p>

<p>Which brings me to Sheryl Sandberg. I&rsquo;m sure you&rsquo;ve probably heard of her, the Facebook exec who has been making BIG waves with her book <em>Lean In: Women, Work, and the Will to Lead</em>. I never paid much attention to her, and I didn&rsquo;t really buy into the hype around her message. And then I saw her Ted Talk from 2010. Have I mentioned how much I LOVE Ted Talks? I do. So I watched her Ted Talk, and she drew me in. She&rsquo;s articulate, funny, and easy to follow. Needless to say, <em>Lean In: Women, Work, and the Will to Lead</em> has now made it onto my Christmas time reading list (ah, the luxury that awaits). She talked about several things, but the main one that stuck with me was this:</p>

<p><strong>Sit at the table.</strong> She told a story about how two women accompanied an exec to a meeting, and they declined to sit at the table and instead sat in two chairs against the wall. These were not lowly assistants&mdash;they were managers and major players in their company. And they declined to sit at the table. Sometimes I can feel that tendency in myself&mdash;the desire to withdrawal, to sit back, to not make a waves. I don&rsquo;t know if this is partly my Southern upbringing (wouldn&rsquo;t want to offend anyone, now would we?), my natural introvert and go with the flow personality, or perhaps, a tinge of intimidation and fear or being judged for not saying the perfect thing. So whether it&rsquo;s code, an outing with my fellow developer friends, or just being honest about how I feel&mdash; I&rsquo;m going to sit at the table.</p>

<p>I had someone tell me recently that I &ldquo;could be a lady or be an equal in New York.&rdquo; Well you know what? I don&rsquo;t buy that. I think I can be a lady, an equal, and an excellent developer.</p>

<p>And to sum it all up&hellip;</p>

<p>“How wrong is it for a woman to expect the man to build the world she wants, rather than to create it herself?” Anais Nin.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rolling Rolling Rolling]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/11/rolling-rolling-rolling/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-11T10:30:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/11/rolling-rolling-rolling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The fourth week is at a close, and with it we have completed a third of our time here at Fullstack. It is almost the middle of October and even though we still have plenty of time left (which I certainly need), I find myself sad that so much time here has already passed.</p>

<p>This week marked the beginning of the much anticipated start of Rails. For those who are unfamiliar with what I mean when I refer to &ldquo;Rails&rdquo;, it is a framework designed that makes web development much faster (once you get the hang of it). It sets up a framework for you to build a web application in, and frees you from much of the set up time and hassle. It is beloved by Ruby developers everywhere. And hopefully, with more time I will develop the same love and appreciation for the gift to all developers that is Rails. For a Rails newbie it can seem like magic sometimes&mdash; certain capabilities and structures are just &ldquo;magically&rdquo; there for you to use and you don&rsquo;t have to wwrite the code yourself. It&rsquo;s a dream. But then there&rsquo;s the task that comes alongside that of having to actually understand what&rsquo;s happening. I am struggling to grasp some of the intricacies of Rails, but I can see how it changed the game for developers. At this point, it&rsquo;s really a matter of connecting the dots, spending more and more time in the framework, and developing an intuitive sense of what Rails is doing under the hood.</p>

<p>On Tuesday this week we went to a Developers&#8217; Meet Up in the Financial District. It was our coming out debut as New York developers (haha, jokes). But it was a really interesting meeting and gave us another glimpse into the culture and community of New York Start Ups. We headed over to the StackOverflow office which was a conveneint five minute walk away from Fullstack. Their office was everything you think of when you think of a place you&rsquo;d want to work&mdash; great views, stocked kitchen and bar, lounge area, and an open modern floor plan. Some of us may have drooled a little. Anyway, about five start ups presented on the way they were using Ruby in their apps and in their businesses. The uses varied widely as did the products. There were topics that were definitely over our heads, but I think we all gained a lot from the experience. It exposed me to the variety of uses for Ruby and also the ways that businesses are integrating other languages and making use of the robust options and tools available through Ruby Gems. As a side note, Imon and I noticed there were about ten women developers there out of maybe a hundred. The numbers are rough, but you get the picture. This experience coupled with Twitter&rsquo;s recent IPO news (there was a great New York Times article on that), along with my viewing Sheryl Sandberg&rsquo;s Ted Talk from 2010 have spurred a lot of thought on women in tech and business in general. Stay tuned for a post on that.</p>

<p>As a closing thought, and perhaps the beginning of a new weekly tradition, and in light of the baby steps we take each day and week I&rsquo;d like to close with a quote from J.R. Tolkein &lsquo;Little by little, one travels far.&rsquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/04/week-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-04T09:10:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/10/04/week-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>ActiveRecord, Sinatra, RegEx, and Cronuts</h3>

<p>As I look at the things we reviewed this week, it seems like we&rsquo;ve covered a lot in a little bit of time. Each week we hit the ground running, and by the time we make it to Friday I am always left some disorientation as I realize another week is over. Our Friday morning blogging ritual allows me the time to review, process, and remember the week past, something I think is critical to the learning process. As a side note, our blogging process made me think of a quote from C.S. Lewis, one of my favorite writers and theologians, &ldquo;Whenever you are fed up with life, start writing: ink is a great cure of all human ills.&rdquo; I may not be taking ink to paper right now (although I do that as well), but this is close enough and way more tech besides.</p>

<p>All of that being said, I really enjoyed our workshops on ActiveRecord and database structuring. Not only did we learn a lot about how this will affect us in our own ventures in applications, it also increasingly shed light on the structure of websites and user interfaces that I already use. I enjoy looking at websites and thinking through their potential database structure.</p>

<p>We then moved onto our SimStackworld Project&mdash;our first web application. This project started to bring together a lot of the concepts that we had been learning over the past several weeks. It involved Ruby, databases, and understanding how the internet works. As a side note I&rsquo;d like to thank my brothers for exposing me to the world of gaming&mdash;there are many conversations here that I can follow because of the minimal amount of of knowledge I gained through living with you through the World of War Craft and Call of Duty years. Cheers to y&#8217;all. I enjoyed this project, but we definitely still had a lot of help from David and Nimit. At one point David commented that I was in &ldquo;git hell.&rdquo; Yes, that feels about accurate. The building blocks are starting to come together, and I think after doing this project I have a better idea of how I could deploy a simple web application on my own. Hopefully this weekend will allow some more time to review the intricacies of the project that I may have stepped over while executing it. I hope to play around with that a little more this weekend, and I&rsquo;m sure as we start on the web crawler project this will bring forth even more questions and capabilities.</p>

<p>This week I&rsquo;ve been trying to brainstorm more about the kind of projects that I want to work on. Not only for my large end of the semester project, but even just little weekend and night projects to help me practice what I&rsquo;m learning. In this learning environment, and in code especially, I think my best chance at developing (no pun intended) sharp coding skills is to build as many things as I can. I&rsquo;m not saying I want to be a machine that cranks out unsophisticated applications, but I think the act of attempting to write some code on my own will increase my confidence in my own ability to learn and execute, and also give me a better idea of the kind of programming job that I want to pursue after graduation.</p>

<p>As a side note, New York is growing on me in some ways, and in some ways I think I may grow crazy here. I love the accessibility&mdash; you can get anything you want here (cronuts, ramen burger&mdash;that&rsquo;s on the food agenda for this weekend). But sometimes I miss the green mountains, and I want to feel grass between my toes without having to go 50 blocks up to central park. And then there are the strange and confused looks when I tell someone my name. Oh, and I miss my dogs. Also, what&rsquo;s it with everyone here and &ldquo;juicing&rdquo;? Everywhere I turn everyone is talking about how they want to do a &ldquo;juice fast.&rdquo; Mmmm, not me, I&rsquo;ll take my bagels and my cronuts and my tacos. On a more positive note, I love how much you walk here&mdash; even though I sit for the majority of the day I have yet to experience back issues, and I feel overall healthy. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to see if I end up here post Fullstack; in many ways I&rsquo;d be sad to start my coding career apart from my fellow Fullstackers. I can already see where New York would be a great community to launch a career in tech, and that draw may be enough to make me want to plant my feet here a little bit more permanently.</p>

<p>The cronut hunt is still on. I discovered that the bakery is about a block off my walk on my way to school, so I&rsquo;ve started taking a detour everyday to checkout the line. Hopefully when the weather cools off a little bit people&rsquo;s cronut cravings will ebb (not mine though). I&rsquo;m also planning on making a reservation for some cronuts. It will happen people, bear with me.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to start setting some goals. I&rsquo;ve always enjoyed this process and I think it keeps me focused. Normally, I was in situations where goal setting was a natural part of the start of the semester, but with all the craziness of moving up here I&rsquo;ve neglected this ritual. So I&rsquo;m going to start small. Goals for this weekend: recover and rest&mdash;I think I may be coming down with something; attempt the Sinatra Linker project on Saturday (hence, come into Fullstack this Saturday); brush up on my hash syntax and regular expressions work, a little review never hurt anyone; find a ramen burger (I don&rsquo;t know why I&rsquo;ve latched onto this idea, but I&rsquo;m going for it. I may have some foodie tendencies); and lastly, but certainly not the least important, cheer on my DAWGS as they show Tennessee how to play some real football (this may be happening at Fullstack as the game is at 3:30&mdash;but hey, what are our double monitors for if not some live football streaming?). Oh, and I want to fix my octomailer configuration so that it sends out a link to my blog, and not just the content. Have a good one, friends.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two Weeks and Counting]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/27/two-weeks-and-counting/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-27T09:18:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/27/two-weeks-and-counting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Blackjack, Ruby, Databases, and Cronuts</h3>

<p>This week has flown by. Each day is so full and before I know it, it&rsquo;s the end of the week. It makes me realize how fast these 12 weeks are going to go and how I need to be taking advantage of every minute of them.</p>

<p>This week started off with the blackjack project. This project involved two main tasks&mdash;writing the code that would generate a blackjack game between a dealer and a player, and writing the tests that would ensure that the code was going to work the way you anticipated. Using test driven development in real life is as hard as it sounds. Not only do you have to try and write code that executes what you want, but you have to write a test that passes based on whether you write that code correctly. In reality, it takes a ton of time on the front end, but when you are done you know you have code that is functioning how it should (assuming you wrote good tests&hellip; but you know what happens when you assume). This exercise was really difficult at first, but as time went on it became more natural and your brain learns to switch between the two different objectives. I think I&rsquo;ll probably try and work through this project again this weekend, or at least review it again. It was really helpful in conceptualizing what was going on in your code and how to write effective tests.</p>

<p>We then switched gears to databases. I think some people found this topic lackluster and a necessary evil, but I found it really interesting! I love the idea of being able to extract very exact information. It gives you access to so many different things, and is so applicable in the real world. When learning SQL it was more a matter of getting syntax and little tricks down. I&rsquo;m by no means an expert, but I think it&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ll play around with more, especially as we start building web apps and potentially gathering data on users. I think as a student of international affairs and public administration I&rsquo;ve always been shown the power of data, and I&rsquo;m excited to have a better understanding of how to access and use it.</p>

<p>From SQL we transitioned over to a project of building our own Active Record(a rails feature), called Simple Record. Once I grasped what we were doing in this project I thought it was really cool! We basically built a way to access a databse(in our case SQL) using the Ruby language. There was a lot going on in this project, and once we were into it we had hundreds of lines of code. And of course, David showed us how we could condense that all down, deeming much of our code unnecessary. But hey! I struggled through it and I think it was worth it for the cognitive gains. I definitely gained a better understanding of what is going on in Active Record, and this weekend I plan on taking another look at what we built for the Simple Record project and making sure I&rsquo;m understanding what&rsquo;s going on at each step.</p>

<p>I think this week has been a transitional week. Now that I am getting my bearings, I&rsquo;m starting to see the dots connect, gaining more understanding, and getting excited about what&rsquo;s to come. But I&rsquo;m probably still struggling to gain confidence in myself as a programmer. I second guess my self alot, defer to my partner&rsquo;s opinion, and occasionally make some self deprecating jokes (a very unbecoming habit that I&rsquo;m trying to stop). I think this weekend I need to just get my head straight. As David mentinoed in our one-on-one last week &ldquo;The computer won&rsquo;t judge you.&rdquo; I don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;s so much of a lack of confidence as much as it is self consicousness. I can feel it starting to drop away as more concepts click. All in all, I feel like I&rsquo;m on the upswing. The basic concept coding hill doesn&rsquo;t seem quite as steep as it use to, and I&rsquo;m starting to enjoy our projects more. This weekend and the beginning of next week will really be about grounding everything I&rsquo;ve learned so far, and gearing up to take on even more difficult coding challenges. I can&rsquo;t wait to see what the next week holds!</p>

<p>P.S. I tried for cronuts today. No luck, the line was around the block. Next week I&rsquo;m going to try again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[End of First Week]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/20/end-of-first-week/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T09:36:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/20/end-of-first-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>The First Week Comes to a Close</h1>

<p>The first week at Fullstack has definitely been a challenging one. As I&rsquo;ve told a couple of friends lately, &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve never been so intellecutally humbled and challenged.&rdquo; One of the biggest take aways has just been learning how to switch the way I approcah problems and understanding. While I completed nearly all of the preterm coursework, there is nothing like getting your hands dirty and actually trying to build something. This week has really taught me how to take each problem and break it down into logical steps, and in that I&rsquo;ve realized that sometimes the hardest part is just figuring out where to start.</p>

<p>I really enjoyed buidling the profile page on the first day. It was an unintimdating way to get started, and start learning how to play around with things. The hardest thing for me this week was probably the octomailer project. I think I really struggled with just figuring out what the next step was, and it just wasn&rsquo;t clicking. I understand how we were using symbols and hashes and arrays on the more theoretical level, but when it came to actually writing the code and moving through it step by step I really struggled.I reviewed the project with my finished code afterwards and that helped solidfy the thought process a little bit. Since I hadn&rsquo;t gotten to haiku yet, I started on that, and I&rsquo;ve really enjoyed working on building that so far! I really like how I can see the logical next steps&mdash; that project is clicking more for me than the octomailer.
I think moving forward my biggest challenge is just overcoming the doubt that creeps in when something doesn&rsquo;t click immediately. I know I&rsquo;m capable of learning how to do this, but I often find myself doubting my ability to learn and execute.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Week]]></title>
    <link href="http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/first-week/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T12:45:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://hjbuchanan.github.io/blog/2013/09/17/first-week</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First Days at Fullstack
The first days have already been full of learning and sometimes, new frustrations. I don&rsquo;t know if I ever realized how many things can go wrong with your computer&mdash;this morning we spent the better half of the day trying to reinstall ruby in order for me to write this blog post. Luckily, David and Nimit are master coders and I think we worked it all. I&rsquo;m going to download some updated software and hopefully that will help avoid some problems in the future. This afternoon we start on Ruby, so get ready for an update on that!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
